Uh, I have bad news for
you. We're going to
meditate, so please get ready. Uh, so,
because we will finish the long room
in Kyoto. If we all live that long, uh,
save and record
the
meditations. Ed,
dec, this is
someone asking you for money.
We're calling it someone
blackmailing the 30-30-30 program. It's a
day, anyone.
[Music] You
can get the 100
videos as soon as they're
finished. You get them like the
next day, well, close to it.
And then, if you're angry and if you don't support
this day,
we're going to send the
video through the US Postal Service,
which takes like a few weeks
for you to receive.
Understand? So,
think about it. It's a day. If everyone
helps, that means it can be
free for everyone. We don't have to be
asking you anymore,
and that makes us waste time. You know, are
you ready?
So don't forget, if something comes out of this
meditation, it's going to last 100 years here,
saved. It's our
brothers, we're very
bad, we call ourselves the ones who kill you in
bed. You do it
like, silently, and everyone is left.
Dizzy, maybe your child does that, I don't know. Okay, are you ready?
Seriously, ready?
Okay. This is going to last, it should
last half an hour,
but the first one I think will last
45. Okay, clear
your throats,
a little smile on your face,
and I
like to pull my abdomen in
because it helps support your
back.
Try to relax your
forehead and relax your palms.
Basically, you can make any gesture
with your
hands. Just make sure you're
relaxed, shoulders back a little bit at
shoulder level, your
eyes are looking straight ahead but your
eyelids are closed,
so your eyes are looking at the
[Music]
horizon, your eyelids are closed and you
look down,
your chin down. And then you're going to
start to fall asleep, so keep
your eyes open. You're
looking, and we're going to
count 100 breaths. I know we
usually talk about
10,
personally I count 100. I
realize my mind goes to a very
peaceful place. So let's go for 100 breaths.
The exhalation is the first part of the
[Music]
breath and the inhalation is the
second, and we're going to do
100.  Start thinking about
something else. And then please bring your mind
back, and don't get angry, and don't be too
hard on your mind. Your mind, with
love, to your mind. Come on, we have to
return to the breath. So you're going to be
thinking about other
things, and when you realize it,
return to your
breath. Exhale and
inhale. Here we go.
Keep your mouth
soft.
Now we'll do the six. One, the
preliminaries.
The
first one, please think of someone you
really
admire. It could be someone in your life.
Now, it doesn't have to
be someone religious. It can be
anyone you really
admire, someone you'd like to be like.
Maybe just one quality
you admire, and maybe not their whole
life. Maybe they have something special, an
ability to be patient. Or maybe
they have a special ability to
be kind. So think of a
person you admire and invite them to come
meditate with you. It could be a
famous person from the past, or
someone you haven't met
yet. Maybe
everyone would love to. Waiting for the day we can,
someone
who doesn't
have the same problem that makes you
feel impatient with...
[Music]
Someone. So maybe try bringing
someone you know. It's quite something
to meditate
with.
You can
imagine them at the level of your forehead, about the size of your
thumb, and they're there in front of your third
eye, in the
air,
maybe half a meter in front of your forehead. Or I
personally like to imagine that a
normal-sized person is
sitting there in front of
me in a very relaxed way, and that it's like
two friends meditating
together. I enjoy being friends with this
person, just meditating together as
friends. So keep this clear in your
mind and think about what you
admire. What quality do they
have that you would like to have
here?
Now imagine that you
like to give an
offering. Basically, you cover the sky.
First, I think of the
blue sky. I think of the day when there are no
clouds in the sky,
and the whole sky, I like, with
red roses, with flowers. I cover the whole sky with
flowers. It's
[Music]
beautiful, and I offer this. I give this
just to
[Music]
honor her.
And now we're going to make a confession.
We're going to think of something that we've done in the last three
days that we haven't...  Very happy.
Maybe
you felt jealous of someone else.
Think about
something negative that has happened in the
last two or three
days. Of course, only negative things.
Take a few seconds to think about something
negative.
But the point of this third preliminary
is to think about one or two of them and
regret it.
And it's good
practice to tell someone what's going on. It's
very
good. And we have a habit of telling
other people about our
weaknesses, our
mistakes. So
[Music]
as a negative mental habit,
and tell this person, "
Honestly, they are nice, they are
good people."
And
tell them something you have done in the
last few
days.
[Music]
Tell them something that makes you happy, something good you have
done. This morning we are meditating. At the
end of the retreat,
I can feel that your meditation is
good. I can feel that I have worked hard
this
[Music]
week because I meditated with someone with so many
years, with so many people. So they can
be proud of this
work this
week, and I can tell just from this
meditation that they had a very good
week, that they worked very hard. And
you can tell this person about
your week and  Being
happy in an honest way, not in a
proud way, attends a lot. Progress
is at the
next preliminary stage. It's to ask for more
[Music]
teaching. I think most of the
teaching we get is personal.
And it's interaction with other
people that teaches us more than we
learn in class many
times. So today and tomorrow, the next few
days, since you're going to
return, many
interactions. Many of us are going to be
traveling. It's simply a matter of meditating
while we interact with other
people, while we have conversations
with other
people. A prayer that people teach us
some of the things. People
teach us negative things. We see someone act
in a
wrong way, and I think we see that
I myself
teach good examples and bad
examples. It asks us to
recognize someone is
teaching. It asks us to learn something
[Music]
from the
preliminary stage. We are surrounded by
very good people, and sometimes
we get
used to it. Try
[Music] to
think of good people in your life,
be
personal friends, be family members, be
public figures of
us, setting an example all day,
every
day
[Music],
and that they stay in your
life. It asks that you can recognize  To these
teachers, ask them not to leave you, ask them to
[Music]
stay.
Then, after the first six
thousand, we're going to
meditate, and today we're going to do a
very
short meditation, the first of the 100 meditations.
And I think that to
honor the first, we'll do a very
important one.
We want to be in our lives,
and it's a good goal in
life. We can become a Bapa. That
would be
wonderful, and we would be so
happy, and we would make other people
happy.
So, to be a
Bapa, it's very clear, very simple. What we
have to
do is
become a
real Bapa. We have two different states of mind,
two
different attitudes. The
first, I would say, well, the
second is that we would like to
develop the understanding
of where this world comes from, and where
all the people in this
world come from, and where they don't
come from. The second, ultimate understanding
of cause and effect, understanding the
seeds of everything.
We journey to
the... and to get to
that last
bit, there's a basic one that we have to
develop
[Music]
first, and that
is a concern or an understanding
that other people desire
happiness as much as I do. All day, every
minute of my day, I'm trying to be
happy. I'm trying to make myself happy. That's it.
Well, it's a great goal in human life
to be
happy, and the first meditation we
have
today is to think of another person
in your life. It could be a
friend, someone you
work with, anyone, a member
of your
family. Choose one person.
The meditation is very short, and this meditation is about
them wanting to be happy in the
same way. I want to be happy.
Now focus on this other
person.
Just try to
think, they are the same as me, they also
want to be happy, they also
look forward to every moment of the day, every
minute. They are also hoping to be
happy today, every minute.
That is also within them. I know that it is
within me too, within
them too. They are
waiting for every minute of
today, hoping that good things will happen, just
happy. Choose someone, and they
also want to be happy every minute of
today. Let's stay here for a
minute, and we are going to close the
meditation. It's very short, very powerful, and very important, and it's something you can do for the next few weeks if you want. Here we go, one person... we are going to close the meditation. We are going to end this meditation. A good... the meditation is
short, but
mental karma is much more
powerful than physical or verbal karma.
Just half an
hour of meditation is very
powerful in the center
of the mind, and there where the seeds are created.
So imagine this
seed that we create in this
meditation. I like to imagine them in the
center of my
mind, little golden seeds in the
center of my mind.
And then I like to imagine that I am
sharing these seeds with other
people. I like to imagine that it is like a
golden light from the
sun that comes out of the center of my mind and
spreads beyond my
body like the rays of light around the
Buddha, and then spreads out into the world
around me. And I
like to let this golden light
spread first in my own
mind and then in the town where I
live. All beings are touched by
this golden light
because I am sharing my seeds, and
then problems
go away, and everyone is
receiving a taste of this
golden light from my
meditation. And then I like to send it out to
the
ocean. In my country there are
two oceans, the east and the west. I
think that it goes out to the shores, to
the coasts, so that everyone receives a
little of this golden light. And then I
send it across the
oceans to other
continents, other
countries, and then the light leaves this
planet.  It spreads around
space to many, many planets and
the entire
universe, and all beings are touched
by these good golden seeds. In the
meditation I
do, everyone is happier,
and now you can slowly open your eyes.
And I like to stretch a
little. I like to do that with my hands. I
'm not a person.
Meditation is
good. I've been leading
people to meditate here
for years. I
think the
best anniversaries I've had here...
[Music]
Here, good
work. Any questions
before? What size? What time do we have to
stop? At 7:15? Any questions? What should I
practice?
Name the Med...
[Music]
Without focusing on one person, you want to
help so many.
So how can you put one person
there that fills that person with all
the other people? I can do that. I think it's
wonderful.
Once I wanted to do
three. And I think that's okay.
That's good.
My
advice: there's one piece of advice. Meditation shouldn't
be so
basic that you get tired or
bored, but it also shouldn't be so
busy that you
lose concentration. So it's up to
you. Challenge your own mind. If you make
the meditation too simple, you'll fall
asleep, and if it's too
complicated, you'll lose the excitement.
I'll help you.
So I would say you have to
try to judge your own
meditation and try not to make it too tiring.
A box
here. Thank you for the beautiful
meditation. I have a question about
how the seeds are opening.
So if at any given
moment a
seed opens in a snap of the fingers,
and each seed that is opening creates me,
you, and everyone here
in this
room, one seed creates everyone, the
next, and the next, and the next,
am I understanding this correctly? It's a good
question. I would say
this:
we have direct experiences,
like when I look into your eyes, for example,
right now, and
we have inferential experiences, like
logical ones. When I see you, I know there are people over
there, but I don't see them. I can't
see them right now because I'm looking at you,
but I
have an experience of them
indirectly. I see them directly, but
I'm aware that those people have
n't left yet; they're still
there.
So at the
same time, my seeds are
creating a direct perception of you, and
my seeds, one after the other, are creating an
inferential perception of them. So I'm
perceiving a room, but in
fact, I'm only seeing one person
directly, and I'm feeling the
presence of other people. So that's how it is.  It
makes indirect perception a
direct one. The seeds are
coming out to perceive you directly,
and among that seed there are other indirect ones
going there, and so I
have indirect seeds, feeling that
I am on this planet and there are other
people and things like that.
These are happening
sequentially, one after the other; it's not that they
all happen at the same time. A
human mind, a non-Buddhist human mind,
can only have an instant of
perception,
milliseconds. So it ca
n't perceive you
directly and at the same
millisecond be aware of them. It goes back
and forth, the mind goes there
and back.
But the
direct and the indirect are created by
different quotation marks and are happening
sequentially, one after the other, and it's
very fast. And in
fact, that's how direct or indirect
images come out of my mind. So
in that sense there is no difference between
direct and indirect. You realize an
image is forming, the image comes out
karmic.
And that image, by silence, isn't
changing. That
image is a second, so I have an image, an
indirect image. But they are all
images, they are all. It's
very, very
fast and it's
incomplete, it's
like with
little bits and you always do one part and
then the other part, not there, and then you get to
this part and that, it's quite a lot, it's all, yes, stop throwing
things at me, please.
Good morning for that beautiful
meditation. My question is if a
seed never touches the
tree when it comes to correlation, and I
want to have this, I'm going to do that.
So how is it that this is ever going to
touch where I'm going without it?
Can you help me understand this
correlation? My question is why? How does it
happen that one comes from another? Good,
good
[Music]
question. Some questions are
logical consequences of
[Music]
thinking. Having certain questions
means that
thinking people
[Music]
some questions should
be what I want to say on
paper. There is a feeling of ignorance or
misunderstanding. I don't like to say ignorance, I
say misunderstanding. It has to
be a
mistake. It can imply that you don't have it.
Misunderstanding is an
understanding that is not correct.
So,
paper. And you are writing with a pen, and it
seems that the pen is making
marks on the paper, and then you can
think ignorant or without understanding.
You can think that the pen is making
marks on the paper, and it is  It's a
mistake to think that, it's a mistake, and it's
natural to think that
because we think that the
pen writes on the
paper. We suffer, you
stay in this world, suffering.
What do you believe? Do you believe that cause and
effect means that the pen and its ink
are making marks on the paper? Do you believe that's
cause and effect, and that's why you try
to have more pens in your
life and you work hard to have more
pens? But what's really
happening is that the pen seeds are
opening, opening, opening, opening, opening,
opening at the same time. Paper, paper, paper,
paper, writing, writing, writing,
writing. Your mind is creating,
your seeds are creating the paper, and your
seed is creating the hand. Your seed
makes a pen, your seed creates letters
that come out of the hand, but the pen isn't
creating the letters, the pen isn't
making the letters, and that's very difficult
to understand, very complicated to
appreciate. So there is cause and effect
when you write on a piece of paper,
but neither of those is between the pen and
the
paper. It's all the seeds in your
mind putting things there one after
the other
in an apparent cause and effect that isn't cause
and effect. It's about  Making the apparent
happen over and over and over again is the
frustration of it. That's
trying to collect more feathers and
making sure they don't take your
feathers. That's what it is,
and it's defined by
understanding the images that come out.
So in tree and
seed, there's a seed, a
seed, there's water, there's light, there's
fertilizer, and suddenly a
tree. And it doesn't come from the seed. That
seed comes from you, from your
mental images. Mental image. Mental image.
Mental image.
There, it can't, it
's not physically
possible because, as
you said, by the time the tree is already
there, the seed is no longer there. So they never touched it, they
never made contact.
The feather at its tip never touched the paper,
never. And the seed, by
definition, a seed cannot make
contact with the tree.
It can come from a seed,
impossible. So, moreover, being
dreaming, which means that your mind is
creating, creating, creating the seed. The mind
creates the seed, your mind creates the tree. So
I can see what you're
thinking because then we bother
to plant
seeds and they won't become trees.
We call them patterns. They are patterns of life. They are
patterns of healing. Seeds don't
cause plants, but if you don't
plant them, the plants won't grow
because it's a pattern.  There's
always a karmic pattern in this
world. Usually, there are
physical seeds that are planted before you
can climb a tree, and those are
karmic patterns. Those are patterns
that remain true for a certain
time until you're more advanced and
can do
[Music]. And I'm supposed to be
fundraising,
and I have some
microphone funding pressure. By the way, this is almond milk.
Okay, more
almonds. I soak them overnight, they get
plump, and then they're
ready. Then you
put them in a
blender, add a little water, and blend it smooth.
Then you add more water, and then you
blend that smoothly. Then you add
strawberries, okay?
And you make two of
those, and I generally don't eat until
noon. But I have two or three
of these, and then... they don't have
carbs. Almonds don't have
any carbs, so the
strawberries... so you can
be in there,
and it's so
simple. It's
cheap, I can save
time. The second question
about
the physical seeds is,
understand how
mental seeds can follow the same pattern.
So we
can think of correlations this
way. That's one  Good question. Your
question is, can I appreciate
Trac's answer about planting seeds? I
understand that, but does that apply to mental images? Is it
the same? The answer is: it's the
same. A mental seed doesn't produce a
mental image. The mental image doesn't
necessarily come from the
mental seed; it's perceived as coming from it
because you've always done that. And I'll
give you an example from the school of alentos.
And this is why you should come to
the
translations; they're free. It's
years of wisdom. We put it here so it's convenient for
you, convenient for
me,
and by following the
classes, all your answers, your
questions, will have
answers.
So, that thing about the
mind, when you see
the color pink, are you really just
seeing the color
pink in your mental storehouse? You're
observing seeds that are in your mind; there are
no...
Pink outside of you, it all comes from your mind.
That's the mind school,
not the middle one, but it's useful. So
they believe you're only
observing part of it. There's no
glass that's this far away, and
your head, my eyes are here, the color
is over there. And then there's a question
in the mind school: Well, then,
in
fact, when I see the color
pink, I'm actually only observing
part of my own mind. In the
mind school, I'm only observing
a part of my own mind. And then the
question
arises: Why do I feel like it's outside?
Why do I feel this? Why does it seem like it's
half a meter or a meter further
away? Because it feels like it's a
meter away. Where does this come from? And
the mind school says you have
special seeds from the past that create the
illusion of distance
outside. There's an illusion out there,
a separate seed in your mind
that's creating the sensation that the
color is outside. And the big question, or your
question here, comes—not
Alice's—where does that seed begin? And the
answer is:
Never. It means that this
seed has never been there forever. It has always been
there. You ca
n't go back to the first day
in your
past life when you saw that  The cup was
outside, you can't point to it because that
would have to be a seed that
caused it. So in your past life,
you thought the cup was outside of you.
Why? Because in the previous life you also
thought the same thing. Why? Because in the
previous life, the same thing exists.
So
you understand,
people who aren't Buddhists
have problems with this. That's
strange. The mind comes from an old mind, and
that comes from an older one, and that comes
from an even older one. That's strange.
Then a real Buddhist will say, "You
're not strange to think there's a beginning. That
's strange." You think that's silly to
think
because then nothing came from nothing,
nothing comes from
nothing, nothing could come from it. So
someone in my life, or in
my childhood, at some
point in my childhood, must have done
something good. That's an
old song, a movie that was called something or other.
That's all. That
seed
came, the impression that that seed
started it, and then it created a mental image
and the impression that that's a pattern, and
that pattern has always been
there. And I'm not avoiding the question
when I say it's always been this way,
but it's the same thing your mom said
all day long, because that's how it is.